RG 103, Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company
Connecticut State Library
Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company records
1810-1980
Connecticut State Library
Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company
98.25 cubic feet
The records of Colt’s Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company document gun manufacturing at the armory and the company’s subsidiaries, together with outside contracting activities.
RG103
Multiple
Historical Note
Samuel Colt (1814-1862) received U.S. Patent No. 138 in 1836 for the first revolving cylinder pistol and along with other investors founded the Patent Arms Manufacturing Company of Paterson, New Jersey. Due to small sales that business closed in September of 1842. Still, Colt guns proved popular during the Mexican War and with the Texas Rangers. General Zachary Taylor, who was commanding troops in Texas in 1846, wanted 1000 Colt revolvers. Samuel Colt made an agreement with Eli Whitney, Jr., the Connecticut contractor for Army muskets, to manufacture the guns. In 1847 Colt borrowed money from his banker cousin Elisha Colt and other Hartford businessmen to lease a factory on Pearl Street in Hartford, where he adapted the system of interchangeable parts to the mass production of guns. In 1851 Colt's exhibited guns at London's Crystal Palace Exposition and two years later opened a branch there that operated until 1857. The Colt's factory in Hartford manufactured 3,000 Dragoon pistols by the end of 1850, first at the Pearl Street location and then on Grove Lane.
In 1851 Samuel Colt bought property in Hartford's South Meadows where he built the Colt's Armory that was completed in August of 1855. The Armory was topped with an onion-shaped blue dome on which stood a rampant colt cast from bronze. Samuel Colt died unexpectedly in January of 1862. A fire in February of 1864 destroyed one half of the Armory and the office. Some suspected that Confederates started the fire. The armory had been running at full capacity to supply the Union army with guns, its total wartime production totaling 378,000 revolvers and 114,000 muskets. Samuel Colt's widow Elizabeth ordered the Armory rebuilt exactly as it was. Construction was completed in 1867. In 1901 Mrs. Colt sold the company to Armstrong & Schirmer, a New York financial house. A holding company was formed in New York State although the Armory was still known as Colt's Patent Firearms Manufacturing Company.
Colt's produced the first machine gun, the Gatling, in 1867. Dr. R.J. Gatling invented the gun first fired at Confederate troops in 1862. Gatling later moved to Hartford after improving the desgin. Colt's entered into association with John Moses and Matt Browning in 1891 to manufacture their machine gun. In 1895 John Browning test fired his first automatic pistol for Colt's. The Brownings reached a settlement with Colt in 1903 that gave the company all the benefits of the automatic pistol and automatic machine gun patents. The company also obtained rights to the English Vickers-Maxim automatic machine gun, giving it control over all machine gun production in the world. In 1911 Colt's gave Fabrique Nationale of Liege an exclusive license to sell Browning's automatic pistol in Europe, outside of England. Soon after the United States entered World War I, John Moses Browning returned to Colt's and developed more powerful machine guns than his earlier inventions. In addition to machine guns, pistols were also in demand. The Army had adopted the Colt .45 as its standard sidearm in 1911. During the war Colt's produced 425,000 automatic pistols, 151,700 revolvers, 13,000 Maxim-Vickers machine guns and 10,000 new Brownings.
After the war Colt's diversified into manufacturing other products and established divisions for dishwashers, electrical, and plastics. Colt's production dropped during the early years of the Depression but improved starting in 1933. However, on March 13, 1935 over a thousand workers walked off the job to begin a strike that lasted thirteen weeks. The company experienced further catastrophe when the Flood of 1936 and Hurricane of 1938 damaged the armory. Despite increasing output at the start of World War II and winning the Army-Navy "E" award for outstanding production in 1942, Colt's began to experience financial losses starting in July of 1943 due in part to its failure to adopt modern manufacturing techniques, resulting in layoffs. Control of the company changed hands a few times and eventually became a subsidiary of Penn-Texas. That holding company collapsed in 1958 and what remained became the holding company Fairbanks Whitney. By 1960 manufacturing operations moved from Hartford to West Hartford.
Presidents of Colt's through 1969:
Samuel Colt, 1855-1862
Elisa K. Root, 1862-1865
Richard Jarvis, 1865-1901
John Hall, 1901-1902
Lewis C. Grover, 1902-1909
William C. Skinner, 1909-1911
Col. Charles L.F. Robinson, 1911-1916
William C. Skinner, 1916-1921
Samuel M. Stone, 1921-1944
Graham H. Anthony, 1944-1949
B. Franklin Conner, 1949-1955
Chester Bland, 1955-1958
Fred A. Roff, Jr., 1958-1962
David C. Scott, 1962-1963
Paul A. Benke, 1963-1969
Source:
Ellsworth S. Grant, The Colt Armory: A History of Colt's Manufacturing Company, Inc., (Lincoln, R.I.: Mowbray Publishing, 1982 ).
Scope and Content
The Connecticut State Library received the Colt Factory Firearms Collection and a large manuscript collection from Colt's in 1957. While there is much information regarding the operation of the company contained in the manuscript collection, it does not contain the sources needed to trace the history of a specific firearm. Such information can only be found in the company's shipping records, which were not part of the 1957 donation, and which Colt's has retained. For a fee, the of the Colt's Manufacturing Company Inc. can provide an Archive Letter detailing the history of a specific firearm.
The records of the Colt Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company cover the period 1810-1980, though most of the collection falls within the period 1840-1890. The records also document many of the company's outside contracted activities and subsidiaries such as the Gatling Gun Company, London Armory/Agency, and Union Ferry Company. Records on several of the related activities are limited to a single item. Not included among the records are minutes of the board of directors meetings, personnel records, internal office memoranda, annual reports, and printed financial statements.
The principle strengths of the Business File lie in the Incoming Correspondence (Series 3), and the Orders for Arms (Series 4). The routine nature of most of the incoming correspondence lessens its informational value. The Legal File contains documentation on patents. Generally, the Administrative File contains "public relations" materials, including drafts of unpublished company histories and biographies, scrapbooks, armory museum records and an index to correspondence compiled by museum staff. The Publications File contains several catalogs of arms manufactured.
The collection contains handwritten and printed materials, bound volumes, drawings and foreign language material.
Material in the separate manuscript catalog was transferred into the record group. All the material pertaining to the Colt Company in the State Library, except for published monographs and biographies and the gun collection in the Museum of Connecticut History, is in RG 103 or picture group PG460.
A later accession has been added as the Mahron Collection, as well as several smaller accessions collectively as Addenda.
Arrangement
Business File, 1826-1979, Accession: T001481, 25.75 cubic feet
Legal File, circa 1831-1943, Accession: T001481, 6.50 cubic feet
Administrative File, circa 1836-1980, Accession: T001481, 9 cubic feet
Publications File, circa 1850-1980, Accession: T001481, 6.75 cubic feet
Mahron Collection, 1871-1934, Accession: T003190, 46 cubic feet
Addenda, 1810-1948, Accessions: 1992-018,1994-038, 2000-036, 2015-025, 4.25 cubic feet
Related Material
PG400, Hartford collection. See "Hartford - Industries - Colt's".
PG440, Collins photograph collection. Album 3 consists entirely of views of the factory during and after the the 1936 and 1938 floods.
PG460, Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company collection.
Also see the
Index Terms
Organizations:
Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Co.
Persons:
Colt, Samuel, 1814-1862
Subjects:
Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Co. -- Records and correspondence; Colt firearms
Subjects:
Hartford (Conn.)
Document Types:
Account books; Advertisements; Agreements; Application forms; Broadsides; Brochures; Cashbooks; Catalogs; Charters; Clippings; Contracts; Correspondence; Daybooks; Design drawings; Diaries; Financial statements; Inventories; Ledgers (account books); Legal documents; Licenses; Logs (records); Manuals (instructional materials); Patents; Photographs; Price lists; Powers of attorney; Prints (visual works); Purchase orders; Receipts (financial records); Reports; Scrapbooks
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
Following the 1955 take-over of the Colt Company by the Penn-Texas Corporation, the new president/chairman made a gift to the people of Connecticut of the valuable collection of Colt guns then at the armory's museum. Having concluded that the museum at the State Library was the best repository, the Pratt & Whitney Company Foundation transferred the gun collection and the business records on March 7, 1957.
Container List
- Business File, 1826-1979; T001481; 25.75 cubic feet
  - Series 1. Accounts, 1840-1890
    This series contains those financial and accounting records that have survived from the Colt Company. It contains the accounts of guns sold by the "Allies? a select group of Colt firearm distributors. These are arranged in numerical order by the distributor's account number. These Allies accounts cover the period 1883-1884. Samuel Colt's bank account book and two volumes of cash and rent books, 1863-1890, are also included in this series. The Colt Company had some thirty contractors working in the Armory, comprising most of the company's employees. Contractor's Accounts, 1868-1889, provide information on the materials produced by oontract for the company and the amount of money Colt paid for it.
    The accounts are arranged in chronological order by month and year.
    - Allies Rebate Account, 1883-1884 (Box 1)
    - Bank Account Book, S. Colt, 1857-1859 (Box 1)
    - Bills and Receipts (Box 1)
      - 1840-1841, 1849-1855, 17 folders (Box 1)
      - 1856-1857, 15 folders (Box 2)
      - 1858-1859, 1861-1864, 15 folders (Box 3)
      - 1865-1867, 1872-1874, 1878-1882, 1885-1889, 25 folders (Box 4)
    - Cash and Rent books, 1863-1890; 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Contractor's accounts (Box 5)
      - 1868, 1881-1886, 1889, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Series 2. Outgoing Correspondence, 1826-1962; 38 folders
    Partial index to correspondence in Administrative File.
    - F, 1826 (Box 6)
    - C, 1839 (Box 6)
    - F, 1844 (Box 6)
    - H-Z, 1847 (Box 6)
    - C-S, 1850 (Box 6)
    - C-E, 1852 (Box 6)
    - C-S, 1853 (Box 6)
    - C-T, 1854 (Box 6)
    - B-S, 1855 (Box 6)
    - C-H, 1856 (Box 6)
    - C-R, 1857 (Box 6)
    - A-W, 1858 (Box 6)
    - A-W, 1859 (Box 6)
    - C-H, 1860 (Box 6)
    - A-W, 1861 (Box 6)
    - G, 1868 (Box 6)
    - W, 1869 (Box 6)
    - B, 1870 (Box 6)
    - R, 1873 (Box 6)
    - U, 1875 (Box 6)
    - W, 1876 (Box 6)
    - C, 1878 (Box 6)
    - J, 1879 (Box 6)
    - E-H, 1880 (Box 6)
    - M, 1881 (Box 6)
    - G, 1882 (Box 6)
    - H, 1885 (Box 6)
    - Mc, 1886 (Box 6)
    - C-L, 1887 (Box 6)
    - R, 1888 (Box 6)
    - A-K, 1889 (Box 6)
    - G, 1899 (Box 6)
    - P, 1906 (Box 6)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 6)
      - F, 1910 (Box 6)
      - F, 1911 (Box 6)
      - F, 1916 (Box 6)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 6)
      - C, 1936 (Box 6)
      - F-T, 1937 (Box 6)
      - L-M, 1940 (Box 6)
      - S, 1941 (Box 6)
      - G-W, 1942 (Box 6)
    - New York, 1937-1948 (Box 6)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 6)
      - B, 1947 (Box 6)
      - C, 1952 (Box 6)
      - B, 1954 (Box 6)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 6)
      - E-W, 1960 (Box 6)
      - A-W, 1961 (Box 6)
      - A-W, 1962 (Box 6)
    - W.B. Franklin Copy Book, 1874-1881 (Box 6)
      Franklin was a Colt Vice President and General Agent.
      Most of the correspondence in his copy book is directed to the London Agency.
      Letters in the book are arranged in chronological order. No index.
    - Form letters, 1889-1955 (Box 7)
      Form letters were sent to Colt distributors with notification of price and supply changes and information on new weapons manufactured.
      Form letters are arranged chronologically by month and year.
    - Typescript (Box 7)
      Typescript is a record of both outgoing and incoming correspondence transcribed from a dictaphone. The bulk of the correspondence falls between 1853-1860 and deals with matters concerning shipment and manufacture in Europe, patents, routine incoming correspondence on manufacture and shipment in the U.S. and some occassional personal correspondence between Sam Colt and his brother James.
      Arranged by cylinder and follows a very rough chronological order.
      - Series I, No. 1-79, 1847-1861 (Box 7)
      - The following are in the same folder (Box 7)
        - Series I, No. 79-99, 1847-1861 (Box 7)
        - Series II, No. 1-8, 1847-1861 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, A-W, undated (Box 7)
  - Series 3. Incoming Correspondence, 1836-1970
    This series contains correspondence to Samuel Colt and to the Colt Company, 1836-1970, with the bulk of the letters covering up to 1890. The majority of the series is composed of orders and routine requests for catalogs, price lists, parts. The series also contains reports from agents in Europe and the United States. Requests for employment in Colt's new Armory are common in the early correspondence as are letters of a more personal nature from Samuel Colt's brother James. The series also contains a letter book of incoming correspondence from the Allies, 1873-1880. The Allies were a select group of arms dealers who, because of special araangements with the Colt Company, were insured of special prices and supplies. This letter book contains a copy of the Colt reply.
    Arranged chronologically as created by correspondent. Partial index in Administrative File.
    See also: Series 4, Orders for Arms, 1862-1933. Administrative File, Company history, for photostats on government orders of Walker rifles,ca. 1847.
    - 1836-1851, 14 folders (Box 8)
    - 1852-1853, 7 folders (Box 9)
    - 1854-1864, 12 folders (Box 10)
    - 1865-1873, 11 folders (Box 11)
    - Allies Letter Book, 1873-1880 (Box 11A)
    - Allies Price Lists, 1875; 1 folder (Box 11A)
    - 1874-1877, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - 1878-1879, 5 folders (Box 13)
    - 1880-1882, 6 folders (Box 14)
    - 1883-1885 June, 6 folders (Box 15)
    - 1885 July-1886 July, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - 1886 August-1887, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - 1888-1890, 7 folders (Box 18)
    - 1891, 1893-1894, 1899-1903, 1907-1911, 1914, 1916-1917, 1920, 1922-1923, 1925-1927, 1930-1944, 1946-1949, 1951-1956, 1958-1962, 1970, 53 folders (Box 19)
  - Series 4. Orders for Arms, circa 1860-1933
    See also: Series 3, Correspondence, Incoming, 1836-1970. Administrative File, History files contain photostats of correspondence pertaining to government order of Walker rifles, circa 1847.
    - General Orders (post cards), 1873-1897 (Box 20)
      The General Orders were placed by various dealers using post cards supplied by the Colt Company.
      These are arranged in chronological order by year, and within that are mixed.
    - Bureau of Ordnance (Box 21)
      Composed of orders placed by the U.S. Board of Ordnance to arm the military. Over the years, these orders were placed by the various divisions- U.S. Army, Navy, and War Departments. The Army and Navy Department orders cover the Civil War period. War Department orders cover World War I.
      The Army and Navy Department orders are arranged chronologically by the date the order was submitted. War Department orders are listed by contract number and are not in chronological order. A list in the first folder details what each order was for.
      - Army Department (Box 21)
        - 1863-1864, 1872-1874, 1878, 1880-1889, 6 folders (Box 21)
        - Miscellaneous orders and payments, 1862-1889 (Box 21)
      - Navy Department (Box 21)
        - 1862-1890 (Box 21)
        - Correspondence, 1872-1890 (Box 21)
      - War Department (Box 21)
        - Master list of arms, 1917-1918 (Box 21)
        - P14321-2405 Sa, 1918 August 21 (Box 21)
        - P2937-1219 Sa, 1918 February 12 (Box 21)
        - P10740-1933 Sa, 1918 June 26 (Box 21)
        - P15482-2611 Sa, 1918 September 26 (Box 21)
        - P14094-2364 Sa, 1918 August 10 (Box 22)
        - CMG 6, 1917 July 16 (Box 22)
        - CMG 156, 1918 January 8 (Box 22)
        - CMG 181, 1918 January 14 (Box 22)
        - P5820-1429 Sa, 1918 April 12 (Box 22)
        - CMG 3, 1918 July 16 (Box 22)
        - CMG 174, 1918 November 13 (Box 22)
        - P13043-2161 Sa, 1918 February 5 (Box 22)
        - P13095-2177 Sa, 1918 August 6 (Box 22)
        - 14984, 1917 October 1 (Box 22)
        - P9886-1851 Sa (Box 22)
        - 14670-R32; 14671, 1917 September 18 (Box 22)
        - 5662-1412 Sa, 1918 May 21 (Box 22)
        - 18497-2992 Sa, 1918 October 17 (Box 22)
        - P4813-1868 Sa, 1918 May 15 (Box 22)
        - P13264-2196 Sa, 1918 August 9 (Box 22)
        - 47253-143/2, 1916 December 16 (Box 22)
        - 749/15/1442; 1443, 1915 (Box 22)
        - 12962-2155 Sa, 1918 August 30 (Box 22)
        - 1915 January 22 (Box 22)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - National Guard, 1873-1889 (Box 23)
    - U.S. Arsenals, 1873-1887 (Box 23)
    - Orders from Foreign Governments (Box 23)
      Includes numerous British WW I orders.
      These are arranged in chronological order as they were placed by each country.
      - Italy, circa 1860 January 16 (Box 23)
      - Egypt, 1865 September 20, 1866 February 15 (Box 23)
      - Egypt, 1866 May 17 (Box 23)
      - Russia, 1867 December 7 (Box 23)
      - Turkey, 1886 November (Box 23)
      - Rumania, 1915 May 1 (Box 23)
      - Russia, 1915 November 26 (Box 23)
      - Great Britain, 1917 November 28, 1918 April 27 (Box 23)
      - Great Britain, 1918 May 7, 1918 May 8 (Box 23)
      - Argentina, 1933 August 29 (Box 23)
  - Series 5. Tests and Reports, 1857-1921; 20 folders
    This series contains the records of tests conducted with arms manufactured by the Colt Company. Prior to adoption of arms, the government required that numerous trials and inspections be conducted. The series also contains reports from military officers on the merits of Colt's weapons.
    Series is arranged in chronological order. See item listing in first folder.
    - 1857-1860, 1867, 1875, 1892-1904, 1910, 1912, 1921 (Box 24)
  - Series 6. Production Records, 1856-1928
    This series contains those records dealing with the number of arms manufactured and ordered, production notes, records of employee's production and time, materials received, contractors, and ballistic tests.
    Arranged in rough chronological order with some material arranged in folders by type.
    See also: Series 5, Tests and Reports, 1857-1921. Administrative File, Records of Colt Company Production, box 62.
    - Production Notes, 1856-1865, 1875-1877, 1912 (Box 24A)
    - Production Log, 1861-1882 (Box 24A)
    - Contractor Log, 1867-1869, 1871-1873; 2 volumes (Box 24A)
    - Production/ Time Books, 1871-1889; 6 volumes (Box 24A)
    - U.S. Army M1897's Delivered, 1897-1899 (Box 24A)
    - Price/Buyer's book, 1895-1905 (Box 24A)
    - Orders Placed, 1926 (Box 24B)
    - Orders Placed, 1928 (Box 24B)
    - Production notes on Baxter, Universal, Colt Company, and Gatling (Box 24B)
    - Miscellaneous, 1892, undated (Box 24B)
  - Series 7. Stocks and Stockholders, circa 1917-1979; 4 folders
    - Notices, 1934-1942 (Box 24C)
      Most of the notices appeared in newspapers and dealt with dividends, dates of annual meetings, and company policy as it effects employees. These notices were issued by the Board of Directors.
    - Statements, 1919-1948, 1979; 2 folders (Box 24C)
      Contains an important record of condensed financial statements issued to stockholders. One odd statement is included for the first quarter of 1979. Most of these were released in conjunction with annual meetings.
    - Stock Certificates, circa 1917-1953 (Box 24C)
      Contains stock certificates that because of company name changes, are void.
      Material arranged by type in rough chronological order.
  - Subgroup 1. London Armory, circa 1840-1890
    Samuel Colt's success at the 1851 Crystal Palace Exposition in London lead to his decision to open a branch armory at Pimlico, on the Thames, in 1853. The manufacturing phase of the operation was short-lived. The factory was closed in 1857 but the London Agency, operating as a sales office, remained until 1912.
    - Series 1. Correspondence (Box 25)
      As a branch of the armory in Hartford, London agents were required to send monthly reports to the home office concerning the London operation.
      Arranged in chronological order by type.
      - Incoming (Box 25)
        - 1852-1854, 1860, 1870, 1875, 6 folders (Box 25)
      - Outgoing (Box 25)
        - 1853, 1855, 1859-1860, 1862-1864, 1868-1875, 12 folders (Box 25)
        - 1876-1883, 1885-1886, 9 folders (Box 26)
        - 1887-1890, 8 folders (Box 27)
    - Series 2. Accounts, 4 folders (Box 28)
      Arranged in chronological order.
      - 1866 (Box 28)
      - Balance Sheets, 1871-1882 (Box 28)
      - Cash Received and Paid Out, 1871-1882 (Box 28)
      - Accounts of Gatling Gun Co. to London Agency, 1873, 1875 (Box 28)
    - Series 3. Orders, 1 folder (Box 28)
      Contains requests for arms and parts from all over Europe and Australia. The orders appear to have been submitted to Hartford where they were filled by the armory there. The London Armory was apparently just a go-between and maintained no stocks of their own.
      Arranged in numerical order.
      - Orders, 1-199, 1888-1890 (Box 28)
    - Series 4. Scrapbook, 3 folders (Box 28)
      Contains clippings from foreign newspapers, pasted in scrapbook pages. They concern arms in general and Colt arms in particular. They begin circa 1840, over ten years before the London Armory was established. The clippings can most likely be attributed to an enthusiastic early employee.
      - circa 1840-1860, 3 folders (Box 28)
    - Series 5. Miscellaneous, 1 folder (Box 28)
      Contains extract and autobiography of James Nasmyth.
  - Subgroup 2. Colt's Cartridge Works, 1855; 1 folder (Box 29)
    Samuel Colt established the Cartridge Works in 1855. Located in the South Meadows, it manufactured the cartridges necessary for the guns in the nearby armory. As far as we can tell, almost all of the Cartridge Work's employees were women. Not a totally unusual occurence in light of the experiences of "mill girls" in Lowell and Lawrence, the early use of women in gun manufacturing in the Connecticut River Valley needs to be explored.
    Unfortunately for researchers, few records have survived from the Cartridge Works. Contained in this subgroup is the payroll record for October, 1855, and a few cartridge paper samples.
  - Subgroup 3. Brass Foundry, 1855-1889; 1 folder (Box 29)